<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Lambs defence against lyes. And a true testimony given concerning the sufferings and death of James Parnell. And the ground thereof. By such hands as were eye-witnesses, and have subscribed their names thereto. Set forth for no other end, but to clear the innocent from the back-biters, and to undeceive the simple, least they bring guilt upon themselves by joyning with bloody men, and so partake of their plagues. Also a touch of some few of the unmeasurable sufferings of this present age, that all that will see may see, and understand, though evill men grow worse and worse. Set forth from those people scorned and persecuted under the name of Quakers.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 74KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A88354</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99864299</idno>
  <idno type="VID">116526</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240903989</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing L249</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P532</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E881_1</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R204840</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99864299</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99864299e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A88354)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 116526)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 133:E881[1])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Lambs defence against lyes. And a true testimony given concerning the sufferings and death of James Parnell. And the ground thereof. By such hands as were eye-witnesses, and have subscribed their names thereto. Set forth for no other end, but to clear the innocent from the back-biters, and to undeceive the simple, least they bring guilt upon themselves by joyning with bloody men, and so partake of their plagues. Also a touch of some few of the unmeasurable sufferings of this present age, that all that will see may see, and understand, though evill men grow worse and worse. Set forth from those people scorned and persecuted under the name of Quakers.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 30 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Giles Calvert at the west-end of Pauls.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1656.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>In this edition line 17 of title ends "of this".</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "June: 5".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="personal_name">Parnell, James, 1637?-1656.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Society of Friends --  Apologetic works --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-05 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-10 </date>
            <label>Kate Allen </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-10 </date>
            <label>Kate Allen</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:116526:1"/>
            <p>THE Lambs Defence AGAINST LYES.</p>
            <p>AND A True Testimony given con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Sufferings and Death <hi>OF</hi> James Parnell.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And the ground thereof.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>By such hands as were eye-witnesses, and have subscribed their Names thereto.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Set forth for no other end, but to clear the Innocent from the Back-biters, and to undeceive the simple, least they bring guilt upon themselves by joyning with bloody men, and so partake of their Plagues.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Also a touch of some few of the unmeasurable sufferings of this present Age, that all that will see may see, and understand, though evill men grow worse and worse.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Set forth from those people scorned and persecuted under the name of QUAKERS,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>Giles Calvert</hi> at the West end of <hi>Pauls.</hi> 165<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:116526:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:116526:2"/>
            <head>THE Lambs Defence AGAINST LYES. And a True Testimony given concerning the Sufferings and death of <hi>James Parnell,</hi> and the ground thereof.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>ORASMUCH as our dear Brother <hi>James Parnell,</hi> hath finished his Testi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony with joy, and fought the fight of faith, against that murderous Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit which is in the Children of this world, who are born and live after the flesh, hath ever hated and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>secuted him that is borne after the Spirit; and now not a little rages against the vessells where the Lamb is, and his Testimony brought forth against the
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:116526:3"/> Worlds wickednesse. And being in all Ages limitted no fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to touch then the outward body or estate, which is so far short of satisfying his Envy (who strikes at the soule, and eternall well-being of all Creatures) that when the father of life suffers him to shed the blood of his Sons and Daughters at any time, he is much tormented that he can goe no further, being the same that is spoken of, <hi>Rev.</hi> 11. who after he had slain the Witness<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s when they have finished their Testimony unto death, doth not suffer their their bodies to be put ingraves, but in the streets of spiritual <hi>Sodome</hi> and <hi>Aegypt</hi> they must lie, till they that dwell on the Earth have rejoyced, and made mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry over them which tormented them that dwell on the earth, and sent their gifts one to another, that they may fill up the measure to the utmost.</p>
            <p>The same being now seen in this Generation, who have fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med their lies fit to please that vain wicked spirit, &amp; send them abroad one to another throughout the Nations in Books and licensed Ballades, singing and making merry over innocent blood, that the remembrance of it may be kept in your streets, least it should be buried and forgotten of the Lord, and goe unpunished; who are therefore given up to blindnesse and hardnesse of heart, so as to rejoyce in provoking the Lord to arise up in revenge, and so to bring the wickednes of the wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon his own head; which that all might escape, is the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sire of all that know the terrors of the Lord, against such who thus provoke him.</p>
            <p>Therefore least any who have some simplicity in them, and yet know not the truth, should be led away with the error of the wicked, to speak the same things against the innocent, and so become guilty with them that are guilty, by consenting to the sufferings of the just, being tempted thereto by fals reports touching <hi>James Parnell,</hi> as though he did wilfully destroy him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe, either by eating too much, as some would accuse him, or by wilfull fasting, as others would accuse him; therefore is these few things touching his Imprisonment, and unchristian usage therein, published, and many particulars more might be added. Also the manner of his death testified by those who was eye-witnesses, and whose hearts was affected therewith.</p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:116526:3"/>
            <p>First as touching the cause of his suffererings in this his last Imprisonment unto death, which was the fruits of a Fast kept at great <hi>Goggashall</hi> against Error (as they said) the 12 day of the fifth Month, 1655. where he spoke some words when the Priests had done speaking; and when he was gone out of the high place, one followed him called Justice <hi>Wakering,</hi> and him on the back, and said he Arrested him and so by the means of divers Independant Priests and others, he was committed to this Prison at <hi>Colchester</hi> as you may more at large see in a book Intituled, <hi>The fruits of a Fast appointed by the Churches gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red,</hi> &amp;c. where your may read some of their Names, and their unjust proceedings against him. And in that Prison was he kept close up, and his friends and acquaintance denyed to come at him; then at the Assizes he was carryed to <hi>Chemsford,</hi> about 18 miles through the Country, as a sport or gazing-stock, locked on a Chain with five accused for Fellony and Murther, and he with other three remained on the Chain day and night. But when he appeared at the Bar, he was taken off the Chain, onely had Irons on his hands, where he appeared before Judge <hi>Hill,</hi> so called the first time; but being some cryed out against this cruelty, &amp; what sh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>me it would be to let the Irons be seen on him, the next day they took them off▪ and he appeared without, where the Priest and Justices was his Accusers; and the Judge gathered what he could out of what they said, to make what he could against the prisoner to the Jury, and urged them to find him guilty, least it fell on their own heads, as you may further read in the Book fore-mentioned. And when he would have spoken truth for himselfe, to inform the Jury, the Judge would not permit him thereto. So the Judge fined him about twice twenty Marks, or forty pounds and said the Lord Protector had charged him to see to punish such persons as should contemne either Magistracy or Ministry. So he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted him close Prisoner till payment, and gave the Jaylor charge to let no giddy-headed people come at him; so his friends, and those who would have done him good, was called giddy-head<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d people, and so kept out; but such as would abuse him by scorning, or beating, such they let in, and set them on. And the Jaylors wife would set her man to beat him, who
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:116526:4"/> threatned to knock him down, and make him shake his heels, yea the Jaylors wife did beat him divers times, and swore she would have his blood, or he should have hers; to which he answered, <hi>Woman, I will not have thine.</hi> And this she hath been heard to swear divers times. And somtimes they would stop any from bringing him Victualls, and set the Prisoners to take his Victualls from him; and when he would have had a Trun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle-bed to have kept him off the stones, they would not suffer friends to bring him one, but forced him to lye on the stones, which sometimes would run down with water, in a wet season; and when he was in a Room for which he paid 4. <hi>d.</hi> a night, he was threatned if he did but walk too &amp; fro in it, by the Jay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lors wife, then they put him in a hole in the wall very high, where the Ladder was too short by about six foot; and when friends would have given him a cord, and a basket to have ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken up his Victualls, he was denyed thereof, and could not be suffered to have it, though it was much desired, but he must either come up and down by that Rope, or else famish in the hole, which he did along time, before God suffered them to see their desires, in which time much means was used about it, but their wills was unalterably set in cruelty towards him: But after long suffering in this hole, where there was naught but misery as to the outward man, being no hole either for aire or smoke, being much benumbed in the naturals, as he was climb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up the Ladder with his victualls in one hand, and coming to the top of the Ladder catching at the Rope with the other hand, missed the Rope, and fell a very great height upon stones, by which fall he was exceedingly wounded in the head and arms, and his body much bruised, and taken up for dead, but did recover againe at that time; then they put him in a low hole called the Oven, and much like an Oven, and some have said who have been in it, that they have seen a Bakers Oven much bigger, except for the height of the roof, without the least aire-hole, or window for smoke or aire; nor would they suffer him to have a little Charcoale brought in by friends, to prevent the noysome smoke; nor would they suffe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> him after he was a little recovered, to take a little aire upon the Castle wall, which was but once desired by the Prisoner, feeling himself
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:116526:4"/> spent for want of breath; all which he bore with much pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and still kept his suffering much from friends there, seeing they was much sorrowfull to see it; yea others who were no friends were wounded at the sight of his usage in many other particulars, which we forbear here to mention.</p>
            <p>And divers came to see him, who heard of his usage from far, and not being friends, had liberty to see him, who was asto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nished at his usage, and some of them would say, <hi>If this be the u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sage of the Protectors prisoners, it were better to be any bodies priso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner then his;</hi> as Justice <hi>Barringtons</hi> daughter said, who see their cruelty against him. And many who came to see him was mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved with pitty towards the Creature, for his sufferings was great. And some of note said, that if the Fine had but been 10 pounds, they would paid it to the Protector themselves, that he might have been freed from his sufferings; and many did goe to the Justices and to the Judges that came that Circuit, about him, but could get no relief from any of them, as you may fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther understand by these two letters following, one from <hi>Will: Talcott,</hi> the other from <hi>Tho: Shortland</hi> (besides divers others might be mentioned) which are as followeth.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <head>Will: Talcott's <hi>Letter.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>I Hearing that <hi>James Parnell</hi> had received a hurt by a fal, went to see him, and found friends dressing his wounds, which were great and the Creature at that time was sick; and seeing him in this condition, I was moved to call <hi>Edw: Grant,</hi> and we together went to one called Justice <hi>Barrington,</hi> and I said unto him, That <hi>James Parnell</hi> carrying up provision into the hole of the Wall where they had placed him, he being got a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove the Ladder, and the hole yet being about six foot higher, onely having the help of a piece of a Rope made fast above &amp; loose below, he going up thinking to handle the Rope, mist it, and so wanting his stay, fell down, and that he was dangerous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly wounded, and at that time very sick; and that I hearing that a fine of 40. <hi>l.</hi> was charged upon him, I was come to him to
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:116526:5"/> offer my bond of forty pounds for his security, that <hi>James Parnell</hi> might have liberty to come to my house till such time as he was recovered of his wounds and sicknesse, and that then I should return him to the prison and that if he dyed, I should return his Corp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. He said he could not doe it. I asked him if he d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d not judge me responsible; and he said he did. I said to him that he had power to act for the Protector, and that my Bond being given to him, was as good security as <hi>James Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nells</hi> body; he said he would doe it if he could, and wished us to goe to one called Justice <hi>Wakering,</hi> who he said committed him, and offer him a hundred pounds Bond, and 'tis like he would doe it. I said to him I was as free to give him a hundred pounds Bond as forty, and that he was impowred by Commis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion alike with the other; and he said the other laid him in, and he would not meddle with it.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Witnesses hereof, <hi>Will. Talcott. Ed. Grant.</hi>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <head>A Copy of <hi>Tho. Shortland's</hi> Letter delivered to Judge <hi>Aske,</hi> as he came off the Bench.</head>
                  <p>TO all you who are set in the seat to doe Justice for the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nishment of evill doers, and for the praise of them that doe well; Ease the oppressed, and set the Redeemed of the Lord free, without money, or without price, for neither silver nor gold nor precious Pearls set free the Redeemed of God; therefore knowing these things by the Spirit of God, we doe deny that any silver or gold, or any such thing shall be paid for our friends freedome. <hi>James Parnell</hi> servant of God hath been much oppressed by the close Imprisonment &amp; envy of the Jay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lor, in removing him from place to place, and putting him into a hole in the Wall where he did endure much hardship by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son of the closenesse of the place, with smokes and stinks, for there is no vent for the smoke and aire, but what passeth out of the door; and there being no way to it but by climbing up a Ladder, which Ladder not being long enough to reach up to
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:116526:5"/> the room, but he must up by a Rope and the Jaylor would not suffer the said <hi>James Parnell</hi> to have a basket with a cord to draw up his victualls; and as the said <hi>James</hi> was carrying up his Victualls with the one hand, and stayed himselfe on the Ladder with the other hand, and reaching to catch hold of a Rope, and missing his hold, fell down, and much hurt received, and now is much oppressed by the closeness of the Room and evill favours that are in it, for want of Aire, which is much pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jud<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ce to the life of the Creature.</p>
                  <p>So as Christ hath commanded me, so far have I freedome in my spirit &amp; body to offer up my body to be Imprisoned for my friends liberty, if liberty may be granted for it. And as you own your selves Christians, that you would mind <hi>Pauls</hi> condition, who being committed a Prisoner found much freedome in his bonds, &amp; was suffered to dwel by himself in his own hired house with a Souldier that kept him; although it was confessed that <hi>Paul</hi> had don nothing worthy of death, or of bonds, &amp; consider <hi>James Parnell,</hi> and that you will grant him the same liberty the <hi>Romans</hi> did to <hi>Paul</hi> before mentioned; or accept of some to lie in Prison body for body to answer. So I remain a friend to the houshold of faith, who am known to the World by the name of</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Tho. Shortland.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>THe substance of the Answer of this Letter, was, That he was committed by a Judge of Assize, and was the L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rd Protectors Prisoner, and none else could set him free; and if the Fine was not paid, he might stay there these ten year. And then some friends told the Judge of his hard usage, and what a small thing it was he was committed for, namely, for speaking to a Priest when he had done. His Answer was, He cared not two pence for our Religion, give him respect to man. Then it was moved that he might have liberty to walk in the yard; but it was said, He should not have so much libe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ty as to walk out to the Castle door, which was as strictly executed by the Jaylor, for <hi>James Parnell</hi> himself told <hi>Gerard Roberts,</hi> That the door being open, he did but walk forth into a little close stinking yard before the door, and the Jaylor came in great rage and lockt up the door of the hole where he lay, and shut him out in that yard all night, being in the coldest of all the Winter. Thus
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:116526:6"/> they waited their opportunities for mischiefe to him-ward, whereby to destroy him, as now they take all opportunities to slander him being dead, for that envious bloody spirit is never satisfied with mischief against the innocent.</p>
            <p>Then seeing all this took no effect, further then to harden them to encrease their rage, to add to his sufferings, and seeing there was no way to satisfie but his blood, and seeing his life could not in all likelihood to be continued long in that case, there was no little labour and means used to lay it before the Highest Authority, yea more concerning that man (that his life might have been saved, &amp; they kept from innocent blood) then ever was concerning any (if not all) that ever were impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soned these late years of our friends, declaring unto them his wounding, his weakness, and much of the evill usage, and this is not unknown to some who are in Authority, who was most like to have helped in such a case, but could not be believed till he was dead, having their information to the contrary from such as was his enemies and prosecutors, and some who acted the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e things upon him, who then used all their wits to cover his sufferings from being known, and now are no lesse subtle in seeking to clear themselves before men of his blood, &amp; would cast it selfe upon himselfe, notwithstanding all this means was used both by him and friends, to have prevented it, even whilst there was any hope of life.</p>
            <p>Here is also another Letter, which may shew some few of their abuses when he was newly come from the Assizes, writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten by his own hand, to a friend, which is as followeth.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <p>FIrst, The day I came in from the Assize, there was a friend or two with me in the Jaylors house, and the Jaylors Wife sent her man to call me from them, and to put me into a yard, and would not suffer my friends to come at me; and one friend brought me water, and they would not suffer her to come to me, but made her carry it back again, and at night they lockt me up into a hole with a condemned man (onely lay for a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don) and the same day a friend desired the Jaylors Wife that she would let her come and speak with me, the Jaylors Wife answered her, If she intended to be gotten with Child, she might come to me, and such like speeches she gave to such as
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:116526:6"/> come to me, calling them Whores and Rogues Witches and Bastards, and the Devils Dish-washers, and that they skipped out of hell when the Devil was asleep, and much more of the like unchristianlike speeches, which is too tedious to relate; &amp; very seldome that they would suffer any of my friends to come at me, though they came far, and they might buy their liberty that did; yea the Turnkey demanded a shilling of a friend to let her come to me, as knowing that they d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d not respect their moneys, so they might have the liberty to visit me, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they made a prey upon them. And severall they have tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned away, because they would not give them so much as they would have to satisfie their corrupt wills; and also when they did suffer eny to come in, she would thus abuse them with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proachfull tearms, saving she would not have her house com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, saying she had somewhat else to doe then to wait upon them, when as her house is common to any sort of people else, were they never so vile and base.</p>
                  <p>And there was one <hi>Thomas Creek</hi> of great <hi>Coggashall</hi> come to visit me, &amp; they would not suffer him to come to the speech of me, but through the hole of a door; and as he was speaking with me, the Jaylors m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n set a prisoner to pin a rag behind up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his Cloaths, and but that I espied it, he had gone away in that manner; and the Jaylors Wife see this, but winked at it: And when it was taken off, the Jaylors man demanded moneys of him for the letting of him in, &amp; the man being unwilling to give him any, because they thus abused him, he would not let him go out, but stopt him, while the prisoner was about pin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning on t e rag againe, but I espied them, and bid the man be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware of them. Then he came and sate him down in the house, and when they saw they could not work their wills upon him, they let him goe. And thus they make a prey upon the inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent; and when they doe let any come to me, they would not let them stay but very little, and the Jaylors wife would threa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten to pull them down the staires, and set on the prisoners to fetch them down, with many reproachfull speeches as afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>said, though they did not give her the least occasion.</p>
                  <p>There came severall of my friends and former acquaintance, nigh forty miles to see me, and when they came, the Jaylor
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:116526:7"/> would not let them in; so they stayed at the door, wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ting at the door to see me, and the Jaylors wife threw down pisse and water upon their cloths, out of a Chamber window, which did much abuse and staine them, and would not let them come in neither. And one friend came from <hi>Cambridge</hi> to have spoken to me, and they would not let him come to the speech of me, but he was faine to goe back without speaking to me: And another f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>iend came from my friends at <hi>London,</hi> to have spoken to me, and they would not suffer him, but he was faine to goe back without speaking to me; and several the like p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ss<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ges and abuses have I suffered. And the Jaylors wife set others to steal away my Victualls, so that the prisoners thereby took ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage to doe the same; so that at last they broke open the l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ck of my box, to steal away what was in it, not for any want, but from the wickednesse of their hearts. Then one that was suspected, being taxed with it, said that the Jailors Wife was the first inventer of the stealing of my victualls. It is not the victualls that I matter, but their unjust and false actings towards me. And when I have asked them if they would not allow me the liberty that they allowed to murderers the Jaylors wife said I was worse then a murderer, &amp; so they looked upon me. And there was a Malignant Priest brought hither that was put out by the State, and his own neighbour that was here with him, confessed that he was a very drunken profane man, and was one of the hundred scandalous Ministers the Nation had put down, and this Priest the Jaylor had set up to teach, &amp; sent for people of the Town to come and hear him, and put me out of my Chamber that the Priest might teach there upon the first days of the week;<note place="margin">This was befo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e he was put into either of the Hol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>s.</note> and the Jaylor told me that if I spoke against the Priest, he would put me into the common Goal. And the Jaylors wife would have set on her man to have smote me, and she said she would bear him out in it; and upon that the fellow having the great Keys in his ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d, said he would make me shake my heels, but he had no power at that time to smite me: and the Jaylors wife swore she would have my blood several times, and told my friends so, and that she would mark my face, and the like, calling me Witch, and Rogue, shake, and rake hell, &amp; the
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:116526:7"/> like; and because I did reprove her for her wickednesse, the Jaylor hath given order that none shall come at me upon any occasion, but onely one or two that brings my food.</p>
                  <p>Now if here I be u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ed like a prisoner, you that are in Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, who knows the Laws and Ordinances of the Nation, may juge; for here I am committed to be kept as a prisoner, though I am the Lords freeman, and doe know I am assuredly, that he will judge and revenge my cause upon my Adversaries; yet this is to clear my conscience unto you, who under him are set to Rule, that you may not be ignorant of these things; then to be sure if you let Justice &amp; Equity fall, and wink at the oppres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion &amp; injustice, then to be sure the judgments shall he at your doors, at your hands shal the blood of the innocent be required. And so I rest with my confidence in him who will not leave me nor forsake me, for whose sake I now suffer bonds the time of his good will and pleasure. Known to the world by the name</p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>From <hi>Colchester</hi>-Castle. <date>1655.</date>
                     </dateline>
                     <signed>James Parnell.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>This Letter was written soon after he came from the Assizes, since which time he hath been used worse and worse, &amp; about the time called <hi>Christmas,</hi> he was put i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>to the close hole, and many devices was daily hatched against him, and friends that came to see him, to abuse them withall, and make a prey upon them, they made an Order amongst them, and stuck it up on the door, That every one that came to see him should spend four pence in Beer; but friends not being free to serve that wicked deceipt (though they weighed not the money) the Jaylors wife run at them with a knife, and would have taken their Hats for it. And now whereas they would father their lyes upon <hi>Thomas Shortland</hi> in their Books and Ballades, both concerning the manner of his death, and the Evidence given to the Jury, the truth whereof you may understand by a Letter under <hi>Thomas Shortlands</hi> hand, which is as followeth.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>Dear Friend,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>IN Answer to thine, is this, <hi>James Parnell</hi> being dead, the Coroner sent an Officer for me, and one <hi>Anne Langley,</hi> a friend, who both of us watched with him that night that he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted; and comming to him, he said, That it was usuall when any dyed in prison, to have a Jury goe on them, and <hi>James</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:116526:8"/> dead, and he hearing we two watched with him, he sent for us to hear what we could say concerning his death, whether he dyed on his faire death or whether he were guilty of his own death: And I answered, That there could no guilt be found in his death. He then asked how long he did fast: And I told him ten days; he asked if he took nothing in those ten days; and I told him nothing that I knew of, but a little water. He asked me what words he did speak in that time; I told him that when I asked <hi>James</hi> whether he would eat, he told me that he had no need▪ neither did he feele any hunger; and I told the Coroner that I often asked him, and he told me that when he needed he would call for something▪ and bid me take that for an answer. Then the Coroner asked whether he were sick in the time of his fasting; and I told him that he said he was not sick, neither felt or ailed any thing in his body. And the Coroner then ask<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed if he lay by it in that time, and I told him that he rose, and s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>te up, and never heard him complaine at all. He asked me what words he spake in the time of his fasting; and I answered that he was silent, and spake very little, onely bid friends yield him up, for he must depart from them, which words he used of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten to friends, bidding them not to mourn over him for he must goe. Further he enquired whether he received not hurt from his fall formerly out of the high hole of the wall, which might occasion his death; and I answered, that he was cured of that. He asked whether he had his sences, &amp; how he behaved himsef lateward toward h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s departure; I answered, that he had his sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses to the last, and that he spake sensibly, and to as good under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing as he used to do. He then enquired what words he spoke: To which <hi>Anne Langley</hi> answered that she heard him say, <hi>Here I dye innocently,</hi> &amp; she said that she had been at the departing of many, but never was where was such sweet departing; &amp; at his departing his last words were, <hi>Now I must goe,</hi> and turned his head to me &amp; said, <hi>Thomas this death I must die</hi> &amp; further said, <hi>O Thomas I have seen great things</hi> &amp; bad me that I should not hold him, but let him go, and said it over again, <hi>will you not hold me?</hi> and then said <hi>Anne,</hi> dear heart we will not hold thee; and said, <hi>Now I go,</hi> and st<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>etched out himself, and fell into a sweet sleep, and slept about an hour (as he often said, that one hours sleep would cure him of all) and so drew breath no more.</p>
                  <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                     <body>
                        <pb n="13" facs="tcp:116526:8"/>
                        <head>In Answer to the Printed Paper.</head>
                        <p>I Shewed it to the fore-man of the Jury, whose name is <hi>Jude Taylor,</hi> and as to those words <hi>(And after that time his friends several times offered him food, and he could not get it down)</hi> he said fie, fie, he would not own them, they might have been ashamed to put them in. And as to that <hi>(but that he fasted voluntarily)</hi> they deny it, and say they heard no such word spoke. The Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roner did not at all send for my wife, neither did she give in evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, but was at the Castle when the Jury was thereto view the body, where she said to the Jury (as themselves say) the same words that <hi>Anne</hi> &amp; I spoke to the Coroner, so that some of the Jury said, that they were all as one. I being at the Hall, stayed there, and the friend <hi>Langley</hi> with me, untill the Jury came in with their Verdict, &amp; the fore-man said that we find this same <hi>James Parnell</hi> by wilfulnes abstaining from food ten days, and then eating up a quart of milk thick crumb'd with white bread, was the cause of his death. I being present answered, that his will was denyed in what he did, as for what he had spoke, I told him it was fals, and he said a prisoner <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap> it, and I told him, the milk I carried my self, that was no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="4 letters">
                              <desc>••••</desc>
                           </gap>ed to him, but to two country friends that were to watch with him at night, I told him that the thing it was carried in held not above a pint &amp; half at the most. And then the Coroner bid me speak of it what I knew, I told him that he did eat a little of the thin of it &amp; some I did eat, and the rest I carried home againe, for they that did watch had eaten before. Then the Jury told me that they would believe what I said to be true. Then the Coroner as'kd them what Verdict they would give in, &amp; some of them said among themselvs, that he dyed clear, them that differed from them (the fore-man being one of them) were of those formerly called <hi>Brownists</hi> &amp; are enemies to the truth, &amp; they said they would have until the next morning to consider of it, &amp; the other said they were poor men, they would not loos their time, but would make an end of it then, and there they stood jangling together about their time; then the two said they would have half a day longer, but the other would not alow of it but would then end it; then they pleaded for three hours, &amp; they said they would not stay three hours about it, for they had busines to do. The
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:116526:9"/> Coroner bid them agree before they went, then they said they would have half an hours l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>berty to which all agreed, the Coro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner told them if they would have other Witnesses, he would send for them, but there was none desired, nor none sent for. Now these two went away from the rest, and said that they would come again in half an hour, they stayed somwhat more, and came again, I was there and <hi>Anne</hi> all this time; so the Jury met together in another room, and in a quarter of an hour they came into the C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>urt, so cal'd, and the Coroner asked them if they were agreed now, and they said yes, and the fore-man gave in his Verdict, That we find that this <hi>James Parnell</hi> is guilty of his own death, by wilfull abstaining from food when he mig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>t have had <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>t, and by lying out of his bed, whereby he got cold, and so wilfully starved himself to de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>th; &amp; to this they agreed, and took it in. Then I bid them be ashamed of what they had done; first you give in that he is guilty of his own death by eat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing too much, and now you say he is guilty of his own death by starving himself, &amp; here you are in confusion; and told the two sepa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ates as they are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap>t their envy had not long to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue to him, that they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>nvious to the life, and now were envious to the creature and that all might see their conf<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>sio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>, and so I past away, as to that concerning the Jaylor, the Ju<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>y deny that.</p>
                        <closer>
                           <dateline>
                              <hi>Colchest.</hi>
                              <date>12 <hi>day,</hi> 3 <hi>Month,</hi> 1656.</date>
                           </dateline>
                        </closer>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
                  <p>Since the writing of this, I and <hi>Anne Langley,</hi> and another frie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d went to <hi>Henry Barrington,</hi> called Justice, that sent the let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter up to <hi>Maidstone</hi> at <hi>Whitehall,</hi> and shewed him it was in the Pamphlet and askt him if he would own that, and he said, did I think that he made Books? I askt him if that were not his let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter? he said, what then? I told him that there was untruths in it, and I askt him whether he would own them? he said, then you have the more wrong; I told him I should not suffer the wrong, the truth cleared it selfe, they should suffer the wrong that writ it; he said he writ nothing but what he had f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>om <hi>Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seph Smiths</hi> mouth, who was one of the two before writ of. I told him I had shewed it to <hi>Joseph,</hi> and he denyed it as is writ above, and I told him that I met with the fore-man, and read it to him, and he said fie, fie, as before, and he still said he writ nothing but what he had from <hi>Smiths</hi> mouth; he was up with
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:116526:9"/> high words in his will, and said he would give his estate if they did not owne what he writt; so I told him that he must beare it himselfe, and he said if they would lay it upon him, then he said he must. As to that Concerning the Goaler, this <hi>Hen. Barrington</hi> saith he put that in himselfe, because there was a Letter he said at <hi>Whitehall,</hi> which was put in by one <hi>Davis,</hi> which said that the Goaler by his usage was guilty of <hi>James</hi> his death; I told him I could not excuse the Goaler of what I had formerly declared against him, for I told him I would not eate in my words againe of what I writ in a Letter, and put up to the Judge at the Assize.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Thomas Shortland.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>NOw this being <hi>Thomas Shortlands</hi> hand whom they say is their cheife Evidence, and that which he will owne for truth, it may easily be seene with any who in honesty, doth but Compare their Lettters, Books, and Ballads with this Testimony of <hi>Thomas Shortland</hi> and his wife, and <hi>Anne Langley,</hi> by what Spirit they are acted, who sent forth these Lyes, useing <hi>Thomas Shortland</hi> for a pretence who denyes their Lyes, and so doth <hi>Anne Langley,</hi> which was the woman that waited upon him which it seemes they tooke for <hi>Thomas Shortlands</hi> wife whom they examined with <hi>Thomas Shortland;</hi> and now let the least simplicitie Judge what truth there is in these peoples Relation; And also what ground they have to accuse this Man for being guiltie of his owne death, when all means possible hath been used (except what was sinfull) to preserve his health, both by him, and his friends, but could never prevaile with that perse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuting Spirit to shew pitty to the oppressed, and now what re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maines in sight to this generation, but the like reproach and slander to the rest that yet remaine in the like sufferings, as they Come to finish their Testimony, for what Innocency is there can escape the slanderous tongue of persecution, the Innocency of Christ himselfe could not doe it, neither while he lived, nor after he was dead; Nor would that Spirit want subtilty so to cover the blood of such as have dyed in other prisons Innocent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, were their blood enquired after.</p>
            <p>And whereas you slander these <hi>Quakers</hi> in your Bookes
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:116526:10"/> that we have received our principle from <hi>Rome,</hi> It is no more but what we looke for, both to suffer in deeds and words, but would God your eyes were open to see from Queene <hi>Mary</hi> through the Bishops to your selves, and so see your own workes from <hi>Rome,</hi> and how fitt a Popish Law fits your hand and your day and let that of God in your Conscience, and all honest peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple Judge, whose worke is from <hi>Rome,</hi> and your strength you worke it by, surely were we Papists we should not suffer by a Popish Law as now we doe, nor were we thus used till we was led to testifie against the relickes of Popery. And you who say you are the Chiefe Magistrates of <hi>Colchester,</hi> and desire it to be made publicke, accuseing <hi>James Parnell</hi> to wilfully starve himselfe. Our desire is that you were cleare of his blood, in the sight of God, but this way you have taken is but to adde more guilt upon your selves, and place, and so you will finde when God comes to visit for these things; then woe to such who have covered your selves, but not with Gods Spirit, but have made lyes their refuge, then your bed will be to narrow, you must not then be both accusers and executors. It had been good you had prepared your hearts towards that day in stead of sending out your Books and Ballads, which will appeare what they are at that day, when truth must not be shut in a corner; and untill then we referre our cause both in this and the rest of what we have and must suffer from this generation. Onely useing what meanes God leads us too to prevent such as are simple from be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing drawne into these Errors of the wicked, to pertake with you in these prophane things you have published, or for making merry over Innocent blood, or rejoycing in oppression.</p>
            <p>And whereas you Charge him as a hainous Crime for which he was committed, and in your Pamphlet tells of an act by which he was Committed; take the testimony of these men following, and by that the simple may see his Crime, and what Law he broke.</p>
            <p>Wee doe here Testifie that <hi>James Parnell</hi> went in peaceably into the Parish Church (so called) of great <hi>Cogshall,</hi> and there stood still and spoke not one word untill he called Minister had done preaching and praying, and was coming out of his seate, and then there was many words spoken, which are declared at
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:116526:10"/> large in the booke called the <hi>Fruits of a fast.</hi> And <hi>James</hi> passed out and many people thronged after him, whom <hi>James</hi> knew not, and passing downe the streete towards his friends house not speaking any words; he who is called Justice <hi>Wakering</hi> came rushing after him, and overtooke him in the streete, who smote him on the back, and said, I arrest thee in the name of the Lord Protector: Then <hi>James</hi> asked him where was his Writt; Then he called Justice <hi>Wakering</hi> said he had one but shewed it not; So he caused him to goe to a house not farre off, to be forth comeing from thence when he called Justice should come backe from their worship at their Steeple-house, which was done ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his appointment. Then Justice <hi>Wakering</hi> came and three Justices more with him, who are called <hi>Farbutt Pellam, Tho: Cooke, William Farlackinden,</hi> who examined him, to which Questions <hi>James</hi> answered, and when they had done they cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed a <hi>Mittimus</hi> to be made and all four of them signed it, and sent him to <hi>Colchester</hi> Castle to be detained till the next Assi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zes, which was held at <hi>Chelmsford</hi> for the County of <hi>Essex.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Witnesses to the truth of this,
<list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Robert Ludguter.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Tho: Creeke.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>John Childe.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Rich: Norton.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Robert Adams.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Tho: Sparrow.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Will: Broman.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Zach: Childe.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Sam: Stilingham.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>John Isacke.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Will: Bunting.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>And whereas it is reported that the one Twenty Markes he was fined for breach of <hi>Maryes</hi> statute at <hi>Halsted;</hi> you may take the testimony of the truth as followeth touching that thing also.</p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="testimony">
                        <opener>
                           <dateline>From <hi>Halsted.</hi>
                           </dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>Whereas <hi>James Parnell</hi> was fined Twenty markes for ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, as they say, a disturbance in the parish Church in <hi>Halsted,</hi> in the time of the assembly of the Ministers and Parishioners in the exercise (as they say) of Divine Ordinances, which is false, for he came into the place peaceably, and there stood and spake not untill he called Minister had done preaching and praying.</p>
                        <closer>
                           <signed>To this wee witnesse;
<list>
                                 <item>
                                    <hi>John Coot.</hi>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>
                                    <hi>Tho: Gandye.</hi>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>
                                    <hi>Francis Hanwick.</hi>
                                 </item>
                              </list>
                           </signed>
                        </closer>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:116526:11"/>
            <p>And now what his offence was let honesty Judge, for which he paid so deare a Ransome, and for which he is counted so great an offender, and see if these be Christians who thus torment a man f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r speaking truth in sobernesse to them, when they have done, when the Scripture Commands the first to hould his peace, if any thing be revealed to another that stands by, but he did not speake till the first had done; Nay did he here so much as breake the Popish Law, made by <hi>Mary,</hi> let them that know the Law, and are just Judge thereof, and see what Justice he had from these called Christians. And now you who to Cover this your unchristian dealing have devised subtill wayes, by false re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports and sending out your fained Books and Balads, licenced as you say by order, by which you make sport for the licentious prophane ones, and encourage other bloody persecuters, who have long waited for blood, and have thirsted after it as the Wolfe for his prey, and all sorts of people to whom your books or ballads doth come, to them you have piped that they may dance thereto, and you have given knowledge to all both Civill and prophane, of what value the sufferings of the innocent are to you, and that they may pertake with you in your mirth, and so joyne with you to cleare the wicked and accuse the innocent; and now you thinke you have hid your selves, and wiped off all the guilt that can be imputed to you But shall this your Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sell stand before the righteous Judge, in whose sight the death of all his are pretious, and which he strictly will enquire after? Shall it not then appeare that instead of Covering your sin, you will be found guiltie of all this prophanenesse that is occasioned throughout the world, through sending out your bookes and songs made up of deceit, and this will you find at that day to be a Cursed Cover and you Cursed who have put it on, in oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sition to the truth? O blind people who are growne against the Lord till you make a mock of sin, and drinke iniquitie with de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sire, who are rakeing all you can true or false from whom ever you can, from people drunke or distracted, or uncleane, or how ever possessed with the Devill the father of lyes; and this you embrace as a prize for your purpose, that you may cast it upon the Children of light, who have none to plead their cause upon earth; and if any by the light be so convinced that they come
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:116526:11"/> to confesse thereto and then through disobedience draw back againe, such a Child of <hi>Belial</hi> who hath gainesayed the truth, serves you for an informer to raise up a heape of wickednesse to cast upon the truth, though we neither owne him nor his prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tise; and thus you are fighting against the Lords appearance, armeing your selves with the Devills instruments. O vaine peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, will these things cover you? what a garment is this you are putting on, will it cover your owne wickednesse who thus re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce in iniquitie? will this heape of lyes you have sent forth Cover all the blood of this man and others, who have dyed in prisons these late yeares, who have been cast in for Conscience sake, and there have layd till the Lord hath ransomed them by takeing them to himselfe, and the many numbers of innocent ones, who have been and are cast into stinking dark holes, such as you would not put your doggs in, and such as were it not the mightie power of God which preserves that all shall not be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stroyed, it were impossible that any creature should live for such long time as some have been in whole yeares without either fire or ayre in winter or summer; the like having never been seen or heard since this was a Nation, and this is knowne without pit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie or any hope of helpe as from man; and such penalties for no offences as hath not been heard of, as some have been taken up for wandring beggars, who did never aske any thing of any, and being so cōmitted have been fined one or two hundred pounds, and put in a hole till payment. Now how a beggar should re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deeme his life with such a summe, and whether the life was not like to be the ransom sooner or later let any one weigh and judge. And this <hi>James Parnell</hi> who was fined twice twentie markes, and no breach of Law proved against him, and he shut up in a hole till paiment, and so used as before mentioned, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther there was like to be any other thing no redeeme his libertie but death sooner or later, all that knew the man and the place he was in may easily Judge. And how often some who are in authoritie was informed of his weaknesse, and that he could not live long unles he had some liberty &amp; aire, they are not ignorant which is now the peace of many of us that we was not wanting of our dutie to informe them thereof, and lay it before them, that being all we could doe therein and not sin; and often had
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:116526:12"/> they heard thereof had they not some of them turned their faces from the crys of the oppressed, which now is our desires to God that it might not be charged upon them and the Nation, which assuredly will be sooner or later if not repented of. And surely this is little token of sorrow that after this barbarous usage and this effect thereof to accuse the man for making away himselfe, when as there was never so much means used and so many com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaints made for any one prisoner, both by himselfe and other friends to have saved Innocent blood as was concerning him, and this some knows very well who are in no little power in the Nation, and most like to have procured libertie in that case he was in, even as long as there was any hope of life this was done. And now after all this to turne it into a lye to cover you with, and into songs to make you merry with, and so not onely to make him the object of cruelty unto death, but also an object of your sport and a scorne to fooles, and (what in you lyes) a reproach to all the rest of the Children of light now after his death, who are many of them in the like sufferings among you, if you have dealt like Christians herein, or doe as you would be done unto, then it will be well with you in the day of righteous Judgement, when not onely innocent blood but all the imprison<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of Christ Jesus, and who have cast him in, yea who have visitted him and who have not must be enquired into as God hath seene it and not as men make excuses, which in tender love to your soules we wish you consider of, and with the light of Christ onely to examine your hearts herein, that you may see your state now as it will be found then with the same light at that day, for till that day doe we refer our cause herein, having none now amongst men who will plead our cause, nor make en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quirie for our bloody and cruell sufferings, both of bodyes and the spoyling of our goods which we joyfully suffer for the Lords sake, knowing that we are his with all we have, nor doe we murmur thereat, neither here should we have mentioned it, had it not been to oppose lyes, and cleare the truth thereof, and keepe such cleare who are not yet guiltie, who might be decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved therewith. Though our sufferings at this time be such as it will appeare when it is brought to light (as it must sooner or later, for it must not alwayes be thus hid) that the sufferings of
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:116526:12"/> our bodies and estates for Conscience sake in these three last yeares of the Lords appearance, such a number of sufferings, and for such things, As threescore yeares last past of the tyrannicall Kings and bloody Bishops, and their perfection is farr short of. And this will one day appear to your confusion who now makes it your sport and your songs, and may say of all the rest as of <hi>Ja: Parnell</hi> that they have done it to themselves. As which of the Saints was not both sufferers and offenders in the eyes of those who hated them and in their generation, but will not be found so in the eyes of God, nor the generations to come, when the Lambs testimony is finished in sufferings and the kingdome come, and the wicked bloody man scattered from the face of the earth. Then shall the even ballance be seene, and the cause of the poore weighed therein, though to you who are in this scornfull envious nature, there must be stumbling blocks that you who will not own the light may be more blind, so that the further you goe on in persecution the more ignorant you may be of him you persecute, least you should see what you are doing and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent and be healed, for did you know what you are doing, you would not adde iniquitie unto sin to cover it. Oh foolish people, is there none of you can see and consider this once in your hearts, was not persecution ever blind, and is it like you should see, who exceed therein? will you despise the poore, and trample upon the Innocent, and slay the Just, and make you sport there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with, and say you see, and it is them that thus suffer with pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence that is deluded? Suppose it was so, Is not that an uncleane Spirit that can make sport therewith, or take delight to lay open others nakedness for a corrupt end against the truth? who would have thought ever to have seene such things as these to have been suffered to be sung in our streets, but much more to see them licenced by order? surely a lamentation is for you till you returne, how are the mightie fallen, and iniquitie hath taken place above equitie? and so you are returned to the baser sort to gratifie the abominable thing in them, and your hearts are made merry with lyes, but the hearts of such are made sad therewith whom God hath not made sad, who sees the evill that is before you, and you going into it without feare, though such have no cause to mourne for themselves.</p>
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:116526:13"/>
            <p>And whereas you doe this for clearing your selves; our hearts desire is that you was cleare before God, and that no evill might come upon you touching him or any other of us, but we are troubled for you to see you take this way to cleare your selves, whereby you bring a double guilt upon your selves, and even whilst you are about this worke many more lye still in holes abused by tyrants in the like manner, which will be added to the rest, if not repented off with speede, then it will be more seene that you have more desire to cleare your selves from the guilt before men, than from the act before God.</p>
            <p>Will sending out your Books and singing your ballads filled with lyes, cleare this nation of the blood of the Innocent Lambes of God which hath been shed in this nation, whole blood cryes though they have not opened their mouths; as that bloody thing acted upon one at <hi>Mendlsham,</hi> whipping him the like hath not been heard of, as the Country sounds of to this day. Also others taken out of the meeting where they was worshipping the Lord, and sent to prison where they have been most bloodily whipped, without the least shew of any Law broken, or one word spoken, witnes <hi>Thomas Stubs</hi> at <hi>Northampton,</hi> with divers others that might be mentioned, too many to mention who have bin whipt. Will these things satisfie for the many whose lives have been their ransome out of your prisons. As them who dyed in prison at <hi>Yorke,</hi> at <hi>Lancaster,</hi> one carried out in a basket at <hi>Bristow,</hi> which had been bruised in a Steeple-house and sent to prison, never recovered till death, but dyed about three dayes after she was carried out; one at <hi>Apleby</hi> kept above a yeare in a hole without any fire at all, under a cruell tyrant who did often beate them, having eight of them in a hole: <hi>Rich: Hebson</hi> never had health after till he dyed at <hi>Northampton;</hi> one went out sick and is dead; with divers others who are yet in holes like to perish, and others who have lost their health and strength outward, who are released: nay the cruelty of this age is not to be parel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leled; and doe you thinke to Cover all this with your prophane songs and lyes? Is all this hid from the Lord God, because you have blinded your owne eyes, and shut your eares against the cryes of the Innocent, and hardened your hearts against mercy? nay is not this the time for God to take notice of the poore,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:116526:13"/> who are made a prey to the proud, &amp; none to plead their cause on earth, and to avenge their blood, and yet you will not feare him, but adde iniquitie to sin. And how you are hardening your selves in further persecution (such as scarce can be beleeved in this age) even while you are seeking to cleare your selves of what is past; Let this Relation following give a tast, beside much more such barbarous usage in many other places as hath not been heard off, where the Souldiers have come into the Saints meetings, R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d through them with their horses, trampled them under their feete, run their swords through their armes, bailed them out one by one, and set their Pistols to their mouths, and swore God dam them, there they should dye, if they did not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny their Religion; with a numberlesse numbe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of such cruelties we dayly suffer, and if Complaint be to such as should judge our cause justly, and heare both parties, we are not beleeved what we say, but the repo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ts are made and beleeved from our perse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutors, who cover the Saints blood with lyes after this manner. And so that which should be made use on to punish the evill doers, is turned to harden them in their crueltie; so that now its become as a proverb cast in our faces as we passe on the streets; If we kill a <hi>Quaker,</hi> there is no law for them, yet are we in peace, and so made able with joy to finish our testimony, against this generation, till our case be pleaded by Him who dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pises not the poore, neither respects the person of the proud, when your songs and our sufferings, must be judged, and the ground of them, heare this all you whose mirth consists in your brethrens misery.</p>
            <p>The relation concerning Justice <hi>Crook</hi> and the rest in short is as followeth.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A Relation of the taking and imprisoning of <hi>William Lovell, John Crooke, John Sam,</hi> and <hi>Tho: Stubs,</hi> upon the <hi>26<seg rend="sup">th</seg>
                  </hi> day of the third month called <hi>May. 1656.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THere being divers honest people mett together at <hi>William Lovell</hi> his house at <hi>Hardingstone</hi> in the Countie of <hi>Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thampton,</hi> to waite upon the Lord, and as they were mett peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably and quietly together in a Close of the said <hi>William Lovell</hi> (being his freehold) in the way and worship of the living God, and when they had sate and waited upon the Lord a while; then
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:116526:14"/>
                  <hi>Tho: Stubbs</hi> being moved to stand up to speake the pure word of the Lord to the people, after he had continued speaking about a quarter of an houre, the people being all still and attentive; there came in one called Captaine <hi>Pinkerd</hi> and divers horsemen of the Countie troope with swords and Pistolls, who called to fetch him away that was speaking; then <hi>William Lovell,</hi> owner of the said house and ground went to the abovesaid Captaine, and asked him to see his authoritie for his comming upon his freehold, to disturbe those that were mett peaceably to worship the Lord, which the Captaine refused to shew; but asked the said <hi>William Lovell</hi> if he owned this meeting; whereunto <hi>Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam Lovell</hi> replyed, Yea, I doe; then the said Captaine com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded his Souldiers to take him prisoner, which immediately they did: Whereupon <hi>John Crooke</hi> asked the Captaine if he had any warrant or order for what he did; whereunto the Captaine replyed, that Major Generall <hi>Butler</hi> had given him an order to disperse this meeting; whereupon <hi>John Crooke</hi> told him, he would goe with him to Major Generall <hi>Butler</hi> (if he would) The Captaine replyed he was at <hi>London; John Crooke</hi> desired him to let him see his order if he had any; he replyed he would not. <hi>John Crooke</hi> told him if he would shew us any order, he beleeved there was none, but would obey it. And he the said <hi>John Crooke</hi> would use his best endeavour to perswade them to obedience, for we are subject to authoritie for Conscience sake, and it is but equall and just for a man to know by what au<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie he is imprisoned; and his saying he had an Order was no more than if another should say so, one mans affirmation being as strong as another, therefore it is but reason that it should be shewed; but he said, he would not shew it, and so commanded his Souldiers to take him the said <hi>John Crooke</hi> into Custody, which immediately they did. Then the said <hi>John Crooke</hi> asked the Captaine oftentimes what offence he had committed; at the last he replyed it was for meeting in a tumultuous manner; Then <hi>John Sam</hi> standing by replyed to the Captaines words; that wee were not mett together in a tumultuous manner, but in the feare of the Lord, and that he the said Captaine had that in his Conscience that witnessed that we are a people principled against tumults, or to take up any carnall weapon for to oppose or make disturbance; whereupon the said Captaine command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:116526:14"/> his Souldiers to take <hi>John Sam</hi> prisoner, which immediately they did; then the said <hi>John Sam</hi> asked the Captaine what of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence he had committed, that the people might know what he had done, but the Captaine would give no answer, but bad his Souldiers take him away, take him away. And then the said Captaine commanded a Souldier to take hold upon <hi>Tho: Stubbs</hi> as he was exhorting the people to obey the commands of the Lord Jesus Christ; then a Souldier rid in among the people and violently haled him forth from the meeting place, and took him prisoner, and then <hi>Thomas Stubbs</hi> began to read some lawes un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Souldiers concerning the protection of Relig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>on and peaceable people, and the repealing of all other Lawes to the contrary, which the Protector hath taken an oath to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine; then one of the Souldiers tore it out of his hand, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting him not to reade it, then some words being spoken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the rudenesse of their carriage, which made them con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fesse that they were ignorant of what they did, (and also here is to be observed, that the said <hi>Thomas Stubbs</hi> was late before released from the County Gaole of <hi>Northampton,</hi> where he was whipped, nothing being laid to his Charge, and therefore when the Sessions came they did not call him at all, but within two dayes after the Sessions was ended sent him forth of the Towne, and said he might goe whither he would, yer notwithstanding, this liberty these tooke him from <hi>Hardingstone,</hi> whither before they told him he might goe.) The Captaine continuing riding up and downe upon a fat praunsing kicking horse, kicking some downe threatning the people what he would doe if they would not depart and be gone. And afterwards the Captaine com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded the Souldiers to draw into a body, and so commanded the said <hi>William Lovell</hi> from his dwelling house and freehold, and the rest of the prisoners above-named, and carried them into the fields out of the Towne, where he commanded his Souldiers to guard them as if they had been Rogues and Fellons, and there continued them in the field some houres, whilst the Captaine went to the Priests house of the Towne, where were severall Priests mett, and after they had feasted and consulted together, as appeared to <hi>Robert Rich</hi> and <hi>John Rush</hi> and <hi>John Elyott,</hi> who went to the Priests house to speake with the Captaine, and ask<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for him, one came forth, and told them, that he was at din<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:116526:15"/> and that he would be dismissed presently; in the meane while <hi>William Dewsbury</hi> the servant of the Lord cam<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to <hi>Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingstone</hi> to the meeting amongst the Lords people, and there was mooved to speake the word of the Lord unto them; then came the Souldiers and tooke him prisoner, when he was speak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing as aforesaid, and carried him to the rest of the prisoners; about an houre after the Captaine came from the Priests house, and commanded the Souldiers to carry the prisoners along to Master <hi>Snart,</hi> as he called him, to the common Gaole at <hi>Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thampton.</hi> And as the prisoners were going along the Captaine bade a Souldier to let <hi>William Dewsbury</hi> goe; afterwards <hi>Willi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am Dewsbury</hi> went amongst the Lords people againe, and as he was praying to the Lord, six of the rude Souldiers came there, and two of them when the people were kneeled downe, rushed in amongst them, and rid over some with their horses, and one of them laid violent hands upon <hi>William Dewsbury,</hi> and pulled him away as he was at prayer, and said he would disturbe him, and afterwards when the Souldiers had broken the Law, and made a disturbance, and kept him a while prisoner, yet after all this let him goe, and said they had nothing to say to him. And as the prisoners aforesaid were guarded by divers Souldiers as Rogues and Fellons to the Common Gaole of <hi>Northampton,</hi> the prisoners asked the Captaine by vertue of what order the Gaoler was to receive them, whether any other then verball, he replyed, nay, that was sufficient; and they came to the Gaole aforesaid; one of the prisoners demanded of the Jaoler when he opened the doore to take them in, if he had any <hi>Mittimus</hi> to receive them, and he said if they would come in he would re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive them; the said prisoners replyed, they would not commit themselves; so the Captaine seeing the Gaoler would not take them except they would goe in themselves, commanded his Souldiers to put them in by violence; whereupon one of the prisoners againe d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>manded to see their <hi>Mittimus,</hi> that so they might know what offence was laid against them; the Captaine told one of them, that he should see it, but none else, but did not as he said, but commanded his Souldiers to put them in by force, which was done accordingly; Then the prisoners deman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded their liberty of the Gaoler before divers witnesses, know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that they had not transgressed any law, neither were they
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:116526:15"/> carried before any civill Magistrate to be examined, but were committed by Souldiers contrary to Law, and the Gaoler told them, that by vertue of an order from Captaine <hi>Pinkerd</hi> onely hee received them and kept them prisoners; then the prisoners replyed, that hee being the keeper of the Common Gaole for the County, ought to receive none into his Gaole but such as were committed by some Judge upon record; Yet notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing the Gaoler continueth them prisoners in the low Gaole, where theeves and murtherers are kept, and denyed their wives and children and friends to visit them, contrary to the Law of God and the Nation.</p>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>
                     <hi>From the Common Gaole in</hi> Northampton <date>
                        <hi>the</hi> 27<seg rend="sup">th</seg>
                        <hi>day of the</hi> 3<seg rend="sup">d</seg>
                        <hi>month,</hi>
                     </date>
                     <hi>from them who of the world are scornfully called</hi> Quakers.</dateline>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Here also followeth a Relation of the taking and imprisoning of <hi>Thomas Goodaire.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Upon the 25<seg rend="sup">th</seg> day of the 3<seg rend="sup">d</seg> month called <hi>May,</hi> being the first day of the weeke, <hi>Thomas Goodaire</hi> being at a friends house in a Towne called <hi>Old</hi> in <hi>Northampton-shire,</hi> where the people of God were mett together peaceably to waite upon God, and to worship him in spirit and in truth, the said <hi>Thomas Goodaire</hi> being moved of the Lord to speake amongst those peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in the way of exhortation to depart from evill, and to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low that which was good, and as he was speaking in the meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing amongst the people, there came in two Constables with a Warrant from <hi>John Browne</hi> and <hi>John Mansell,</hi> in Commission to doe Justice, and laid violent hands upon him, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d said they had an order from the Justices to doe what they d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d, and so they haled him forth from amongst the people, and had him before <hi>John Browne</hi> and <hi>John Mansell,</hi> who came some m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>les distance from their own dwellings unto the aforesaid <hi>Old</hi> to the Priests house that day on purpose to take the said <hi>Tho: Goodaire,</hi> by which meanes their own publicke worship of the said Tow<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e of <hi>Old</hi> was neglected in the afternoone, for the Priest of the Towne and the aforesaid called Justices spent most part of the time in examining of <hi>Tho: Goodaire</hi> and others that were at the meeting, charging the said <hi>Thomas</hi> to be a dangerous person
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:116526:16"/> and a misleader of the sect called <hi>Quakers,</hi> and therefore de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded Sureties for his good behaviour. Which he refused, except they would shew him what Law he had broken, which they would not doe, but replyed they were Judges of the Law, and forthwith made a <hi>Mittimus</hi> to send him to the Common Gaole in <hi>Northampton,</hi> where he now remaineth a prisoner. And for other friends that were at the meeting waiting upon the Lord, the aforesaid called Justices sent for them to come into the Priests house, and demanded of each of them ten shillings, for breach of the Sabbath, which they denyed to pay, except the aforesaid called Justices would shew them what Law they had broken, which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hey did not, but on the contrary threatned to distraine their goods; all which is directly contrary both to the Law of God, and to the knowne and established Lawes of this Nation.</p>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>
                     <hi>From the C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>mmon Gaole in</hi> Northampton <date>
                        <hi>the</hi> 27<seg rend="sup">th</seg>
                        <hi>day of the</hi> 3<seg rend="sup">d</seg>
                        <hi>month,</hi>
                     </date>
                     <hi>from them who of the world are scornfully called</hi> Quakers.</dateline>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>HEre is also a relation of the present unjust sufferings of <hi>Tho: Jobson</hi> and <hi>William Holmes</hi> now prisoners in <hi>Cambridge,</hi> fined twenty pounds &amp; close prisoners till payment, their wives and children denyed to come to them. Who suffer under a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of entertaining <hi>Ranters,</hi> but denyes all <hi>Ranters</hi> and their filthy practices, and ownes the doctrine of Christ, which is to entertaine strangers, and for the entertaining of some of those people called <hi>Quakers,</hi> they thus suffer by that murderous en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vious spirit, who will neither own the doctrine of Christ them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves, nor suffer others. A miserable Liberty and Protection that after these men have fought for their liberty against tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, should now by the same malignant spirit thus suffer but for entertaining their owne friends into their owne houses, who are troublesome to none; neither can the Law accuse them of any misbehaviour; And now seeing these men cannot for Conscience sake serve the wills of these Enemies of Christ to pay them these unjust sums of money for obeying the doctrine of Christ, and so Consent that wickednesse be set up by a Law▪ &amp; the Commands of the Lord Jesus Christ thrust out, (which they cannot doe, but deny Christ to save themselves) Let every honest man see
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:116526:16"/> and consider what is like to be the ransome of these men, sooner or later, if not their lives, being cast into a hole amongst Fellons and murderers, and Condemned persons, and such like, whose envie is no lesse against them than the same spirit that Casts them in, and so they suffer by both, and must doe untill the Lord release them, and when the lives of these comes to be sacrificed up with others of their brethren, it is not like that the murther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er will Confesse guilty, if a lying booke or a Ballade may ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuse him, for the lyer and the murtherer is one.</p>
               <p>Also <hi>Myles Bareman,</hi> a man of repute in the world, who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing moved of the Lord to goe a hundred miles or more to visite two of his friends who were prisoners in the Towne of <hi>Staff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rd,</hi> was taken in that towne, and by the Mayor committed to pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son, and was twice whipped in the pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>son, and much other hard usage; and this was done without the transgression of any Law, but onely by the envie of the wicked one, who pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>secutes the seed of God, where ever it is brought forth. Also <hi>Myles We<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nington,</hi> who being moved to visit his friend the said prisoner in that towne, and going to the Mayor and asking him in sober<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, what he had committed his said friend to prison for, was himselfe sent to prison by the Mayor, and cast into the dungeo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, and there was whipped in like manner, contrary to Justice, or mercy, or civility, or naturall affection, and many such like tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters are and have been inflicted upon the innocent by barbarous brutish men, who are intrusted in authoritie, by which many have been brought to their death; some of which, having been related to them who should remed, such things, the Complaints could never be beleeved, neither doth it serve that these things are related, but to leave the Nation without excuse; for men hearts are growne voyd of pi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ty, yet doe we know where mercy is, and on him we wai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e in the deep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>st suff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rings.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A Relation concerning <hi>Dorothy Waughs</hi> cruell usage by the Mayor of <hi>Carlile.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>UPon the 7<seg rend="sup">th</seg> day about the time called <hi>Michaelmas</hi> in the yeare of the worlds account 1655. I was moved of the Lord to goe into the market of <hi>Carlile,</hi> to speake against all de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit &amp; ungodly practices, and the Mayors Officer came and vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lently haled me off the Crosse, and put me in prison, not having any thing to lay to my Charge, and presently the Mayor came
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:116526:17"/> up where I was, and asked me from whence I came; and I said cut of <hi>Egypt</hi> where thou lodgest; But after these words, he was so violent &amp; full of passion he scarce asked me any more Questi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, but called to one of his followers to bring the bridle, as he called it to put upon me, and was to be on three houres, and that which they called so was like a steele cap and my hatt being vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lently pluckt off, which was pinned to my head, whereby they tare my Clothes to put on their bridle as they called it, which was a stone weight of Iron by the relation of their own Genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, &amp; three barrs of Iron to come over my face, and a peece of it was put in my mouth, which was so unreasonable big a thing for that place as cannot be well related, which was locked to my head, and so I stood their time with my hands bound behind me with the stone weight of Iron upon my head, and the bitt in my mouth to keep me from speaki<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>g, And the Mayor said he would make me an Example to all that should ever come in that name. And the people to see me so violently abused were broken into teares, but he cryed out on them and said, for foolish piety, one may spoile a whole Cittie. And the man that kept the prison-doore demanded two-pence of every one that came to see me while their bridle remained upon me; Afterwards it was taken off and they kept me in prison for a little season, and after a while the Mayor came up againe and caused it to be put on againe, and sent me out of the Cittie with it on, and gave me very vile and unsavoury words, which were not fit to proceed out of any mans mouth, and charged the Officer to whip me out of the Towne, from Constable to Constable to send me, till I came to my owne home, when as they had not any thing to lay to my Charge.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>D. W.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="conclusion">
            <p>And all these things are but a tast of the whole, inflicted upon the body of Christ in this Nation, whom he hath made confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mable to himselfe to undergo the envie of the wicked, till death, and after their death they are not satisfied, neither was they up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him, who gave large money to raise lies upon him, when their envie could reach no further, and it is enough that his servants be as their Lord; for which of all the members of Christ have not suffered by this generation of men that live in their lusts, yet herein we rejoyce that his peace is with us, and that we are justified in his sight not to suffer as evill doers, though in the sight of men we be so accounted.</p>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>